<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>About OSL</esp:name>
  <esp:title>About OSL</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>OSL is the working sign list of the Oracc project: it changes
      often and as of the reboot of the end of February 2024 it is
      versioned starting from 1.0 and timestamped using the end of the
      build process.</p>

      <p>Because it is constantly being improved and evolved we
      recommend that if you are using the OSL data you configure
      things so that you can update the data from time to time.</p>

      <esp:sh>OSL Source File</esp:sh>
      
      <p>You can view/download the OSL source file <esp:link
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/oracc/osl/master/00lib/osl.asl">directly
      from the github repository</esp:link>.</p>

      <p>The file-format is described in the <esp:link page="asl">ASL/OSL
      page</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:sh>OSL Derivatives</esp:sh>

      <p>The source file <code>osl.asl</code> is also available in
      <esp:link url="/osl/downloads/sl.xml">XML</esp:link> and
      <esp:link url="/osl/downloads/sl.json">JSON</esp:link> formats.
      The two formats are generated by library routines which take a
      single version of the data and express it as both XML and JSON,
      so the content of both XML and JSON is the same. The derived
      formats include computed data such as the homophones and certain
      kinds of imported data, such as the statistics and Sumerian
      lemmata.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>OIDs</esp:sh>

      <p>OIDs are Oracc's persistent IDs: the OIDs associated with OSL
      are permanent and are guaranteed to resolve to something even if
      a sign is deleted or renamed.  OSL OIDs provide permanent way of
      referring to sign pages using the template
      <code>http://oracc.org/osl/signlist/[OID]</code>, e.g.,
      <code>http://oracc.org/osl/signlist/o0000087</code>.</p>

      <esp:sh>OSL and Unicode</esp:sh>

      <p>OSL is not part of the Unicode Standard or other Unicode
      specification. However, it is recommended by a preliminary
      document as the source of data such as sign values and
      correspondences to other sign lists, which are in practice
      needed to use the Unicode Sumero-Akkadian cuneiform characters.
      See <esp:link url="https://www.unicode.org/reports/tr56/">Draft
      Unicode Technical Report #56, “Unicode Cuneiform Sign
      Lists”</esp:link>, edited by Robin Leroy.</p>
            
      <esp:sh>OSL Licence</esp:sh>

      <p>The OSL source file and all of the data that is part of the
      public OSL <esp:link url="https://github.com/oracc/osl">github
      repository</esp:link> is released under a CC0 licence into the
      public domain.</p>

    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
