<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>ASL @glyf</esp:name>
  <esp:title>ASL @glyf</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>Notes on the new ASL @glyf tag as of 2025-02-18 [not fully implemented]</p>

<esp:h>Purpose</esp:h>

<p>@glyf supports non-contrastive variant (proto-)cuneiform glyphs for
@form and @sign and provides a place to define an ATF notation for
accessing them, their permanent location in the Oracc PUA, and their
accessibility via IVS as well as OpenType Font Features. This provides
a machine-readable way of recording in PCSL and OSL glyphs that are
not encoded as Unicode characters.</p>

<p>Note that @glyf is intended to support general, persistent recording
of only a selected subset of variant glyphs.  Many glyph variants will
exist beyond the definition of @glyf, accessible through font features
in specialized fonts.  For Oracc cuneiform fonts, each font has a
table giving details on the availability of variants which are
otherwise only defined within the fonts themselves.</p>

<p>The primary reasons for selecting variants for recording as @glyfs is
their presence in a major sign list (e.g., the CDLI github-repository
of Proto-Cuneiform signs) or their function as a significant
structural variant of a sign where the structural variant is not
deemed appropriate for encoding as a character (e.g., the various
avatars of DE₂ as UMUM@s, |UMUM×KASKAL|, |UMUM×PA|).</p>


<esp:h>Location</esp:h>

<p>@glyf may occur zero or more times in the body of an @sign or @form;
this @sign or @form is referred to as the @glyf's parent.</p>

<p>@glyf entries must come at the end of the parent @sign block,
immediately before any @form, or at the end of the parent @form block,
immediately before the '@@'.</p>

<p>@glyf entries have no corresponding end tag; @glyf is terminated by
the next `@glyf', `@form', or `@end sign'.</p>


<esp:h>Syntax</esp:h>

	<blockquote><code>@glyf TAG UNI PUA IVS? OTF</code></blockquote>

	<dl>
    <dt>TAG</dt><dd>is an allomorph or graphetic tag which is unique among the
	@glyfs which are the direct children of the parent; the
	transliteration for the @glyf is the concatenation of the
	parent sign name and the tag.  Allograph tags begin with '~',
	then a letter, then zero or more alphanumerics.  In PCSL @glyf
	allograph tags may only begin with '~v' followed by digits; in
	PCSL these '~v' tags are reserved for use in @glyf and may not
	occur elsewhere in PCSL names.  Graphetic tags start with a
	'\' followed by digits.</dd>

    <dt>UNI</dt><dd>is the Unicode character literal of the following PUA
	assignment.</dd>

    <dt>PUA</dt><dd>is the permanent location of the @glyf in the Oracc PUA;
	@glyf PUA assignments start at U+FA000 in the Oracc PUA.</dd>

    <dt>IVS</dt><dd>is an optional Ideographic Variation Sequence character
	which uniquely identifies the @glyf when it follows the
	Unicode value of the parent. IVS are given as uppercase E
	followed by four hex digits.</dd>

    <dt>OTF</dt><dd>is zero or more OpenType Features which can be used to access
	the @glyf.  These may be SALT (.[0-9]+); CVNN character
	variations; or SSET Stylistic set codes.  Note that each OFF
	must begin with a '.' (period); this is part of the syntax of
	OTFs in @glyfs.</dd>

	</dl>


<esp:h>Restrictions</esp:h>

<p>A @glyf tag may not occur within the name of a @sign or @form.  In
PCSL this means that KUŠU₂~a would be a legal sign or form name, but
SAG~v1 would not.</p>

<esp:h>Examples</esp:h>

<pre>
(1)

@sign SAG
@oid o0901677
@list U+12AA9
@ucun 𒪩
@uname SAG
@uage 1
@list ZATU437
@glyf \1 󺀀 FA000 E0001 .1 .cv01 .ss04
@glyf \2 󺀁 FA001 E0002 .2 .cv02
@list BAU228
@end sign
</pre>

<esp:sh>Notes on Example (1)</esp:sh>

<ul>
<li>@glyfs do not have an OID assignment.  Where they require one, an
XML:ID compliant version should be created by mapping '~' to '_' and
'\' to '-' and appending the result to the OID of the parent.</li>

<li>Only @sign or @form have the usual Unicode information.</li>

<li>A @glyf may have metadata elements like @list or @sys, but should
not have a Unicode `@list U+' entry.</li>
</ul>

<pre>
(2)

[[ ADD EXAMPLE USING @form ]]
</pre>

    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
