<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>OGSL Ideographic Variation</esp:name>
  <esp:title>OGSL Ideographic Variation</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>This page describes an experimental implementation of Unicode
      Ideographic Variation Sequences as defined in <esp:link
      url="https://unicode.org/reports/tr37">Unicode Technical Report
      37 (referred to as TR37 in the following).</esp:link> in
      OGSL/GDL. The original idea of using these with Unicode
      cuneiform is owed to Robin LeRoy.</p>

      <esp:h>Overview</esp:h>

      <p>Unicode IVSs provide a means for selecting glyph variants in
      a standardized way.  They work as a character pair in which the
      second character is a selector for a glyph variant of the first.
      The selectors are in the range U+E0100-U+E01EF.</p>

      <p>The Unicode Ideographic Variation Database, IVD, as defined
      in TR37 is very simple: a collection must be registered with
      basic metadata. A complementary file defines sequences in the
      collection consisting of pairs of base characters and variation
      selectors along with a collection name and a name for the
      sequence.</p>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OGSL Collection</esp:h>

      <p>The name of the Oracc OGSL collection is
      <code>Oracc_OGSL</code>. This implementation is presently
      unregistered, but the collection data would be of the form:</p>

      <pre>
	Oracc_OGSL;[A-Z]+[0-9]*(?:[@%&amp;*.][A-Z]+[0-9]*)*_[A-Z]+[0-9]*(?:[@%&amp;*.][A-Z]+[0-9]*)*;http://oracc.org/ogsl/ivs/
      </pre>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OGSL Name Structure</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc_OGSL names consist of a BASESIGN, underscore character,
      '_', VARDATA.  Both BASESIGN, the sign subject to variation, and
      VARDATA, the variation, consist of uppercase letters A-Z
      followed by optional digits 0-9.</p>

      <p>The BASESIGN is always derived from an OGSL sign name
      translating subscript digits to regular digits and substituting
      SH for Š, e.g., <code>MU</code>, <code>NI2</code>, or
      <code>SHU</code>.  For compound signs the sign name is
      simplified by omitting vertical bars and parentheses and mapping
      any TIMES sign to '*', e.g., <code>|GA₂×AN|</code> would be
      specified as <code>GA2*AN</code>.</p>

      <p>The VARDATA is either an OGSL sign name or a descriptive
      label for the variant selected via the sequence as described
      further in the next section.</p>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OGSL use of Variation Selectors</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc_OGSL defines IVSs for two reasons:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>To support splits and mergers</li>
	<li>To support variant forms</li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>The following IVS uses are initally defined:</p>

      <pre>
	E0100 MERGER0
	E0101 MERGER1
	E0103 MERGER2
	E0103 MERGER3

	E0110 VFORM0
	E0111 VFORM1
	E0113 VFORM2
	E0113 VFORM3
      </pre>

      <p>It remains to be seen whether the life history of any
      individual sign exhibits this level of variation.</p>

      <esp:h>Sample Oracc_OGSL IVS entries</esp:h>

      <p>The most common use of Oracc_OGSL IVS will be to handle
      mergers--a number of sign distinctions in Early Dynastic writing
      become lost over time, for example IM and NI₂ are separate signs
      in ED Fara but are merged in almost every other script
      phase. This can be expressed as the following IVS entry:</p>

      <pre>      
	# IM merges with NI2 except for ED Fara
	1214E E0100 Oracc_OGSL IM_NI2
      </pre>
      
      <p>Systemic sign variation is also handled using IVS entries.  A
      variation of the MU sign, mostly associated with ED Adab, is to
      form the SHE-style component of the sign with a KASKAL-style
      component instead:</p>

      <pre>
	# MU sign with KASKAL-style replacement for normal SHE-style component
	1222C E0110 Oracc_OGSL MU_KASKAL
      </pre>

      <p>In the case of variant forms, The VARDATA component of the
      label <code>MU_KASKAL</code> may qualify the variation rather
      than defining the target form as a merged sign.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
