<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>OpenType Features</esp:name>
  <esp:title>OpenType Features</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
 
      <esp:h>OpenType Features</esp:h>

      <esp:p>OpenType is a widely-used font type created by Microsoft
      and Adobe which provides many features for advanced typography.
      Oracc uses only three OpenType features at present: SSET, SALT,
      and LIGA.</esp:p>
      
      <esp:sh>Sylistic Sets (SSET)</esp:sh>
      
      <p>An OpenType font can have up to twenty Stylistic Sets,
      indicated as ss01, ss02 .. ss20.  Oracc uses SSET for
      collections of variations which correspond to usages typical of
      a period, styles related to a medium, or general handwriting
      styles.  For example, Oracc uses ss01 for early writing styles
      which exhibit certain mergers that take place immediately after
      the Fara period; ss02 for middle period mergers; ss03 for later
      mergers and splits.  Sset ss04 is reserved for monumental
      script--so a Neo-Babylonian font could have sign forms typical
      of writing on stone in ss04, for example. Sset ss05 is reserved
      for cursive style writing.</p>

      <esp:sh>Character Variants (CVNN)</esp:sh>

      <p>An OpenType font may have up to ninety-nine character
      variants.  The following explananation of CVNN is to be found in
      the <esp:link
      url="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/spec/features_ae#tag-cv01--cv99">Learn/Microsoft
      Typography description of Tag: 'cv01' – 'cv99'</esp:link>:</p>

      <blockquote>
	The function of these features is similar to the function of
	the Stylistic Alternates feature ('salt') and the Stylistic
	Set features (see 'ss01' – 'ss20'). Whereas the Stylistic Set
	features assume recurring stylistic variations that apply to a
	broad set of Unicode characters, however, these features are
	intended for scenarios in which particular characters have
	variations not applicable to a broad set of characters. The
	Stylistic Alternates feature provides access to glyph variants
	but does not allow an application to control these on a
	character-by-character basis; the Character Variant features
	provide the greater granularity of control.
      </blockquote>

      <p>The kinds of character variation that Oracc might use with
      CV--stacking pattern variations, character composition
      variations--can also be supported with IVS (see above).  Because
      of the 99 CV limit imposed by OpenType fonts it is preferable to
      support these kinds of variation through the IVS mechanism.</p>

      <p>It is likely that Oracc will use CVNN to provide alternate
      groups of sign-forms in certain fonts.  For example, an Early
      Dynastic font may have reference forms in the primary set, Fara
      forms in ss01, and Abu Salabikh in ss02.  In addition,
      important groups of texts such as the Blau Monuments or CBS
      10000 and related documents could have distinctive sign forms
      implemented via the CVNN feature.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>Stylistic Alternates (SALT)</esp:sh>

      <p>Oracc uses SALT to support creating fonts which contain
      examples of minor variations in form that may be specific to an
      instance, a scribe, or a school--many sign lists that are
      restricted to a particular period or corpus demonstrate several
      variant forms of signs, and a font that emulates such a list can
      use SALT to encode these variants.</p>

      <p>SALT variations are font-specific and do not need to be
      aligned or harmonized across fonts.</p>

      <esp:sh>Ligatures (LIGA)</esp:sh>

      <p>There are several kinds of OpenType ligatures, but Oracc
      consistently uses the LIGA feature ("Standard Ligatures") which
      are automatically selected in a font when the components occur
      in sequence.</p>

      <p>Some ligatures are defined to work only when there is a
      U+200D, Zero-Width Joiner (ZWJ) character between the
      components.  For example, this allows the sequence diŋir-en to
      be treated as two characters or a single ligatured character as
      required (scribes sometimes mix their use on a single
      tablet).</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>

