<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Oracc Cuneiform Fonts</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Oracc Cuneiform Fonts</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <esp:h>Introduction</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc provides a number of cuneiform fonts which aim to
      provide some degree of consistency and standardization in their
      approach to character definition and use of font technology.
      This is possible even when the Oracc fonts are versions of fonts
      which were not originally intended for use on Oracc but which
      have been generously licensed under terms which permit modifying
      them in the ways required for alignment with Oracc font
      approaches.</p>

      <p>Oracc fonts are all based on Unicode, and make use of both
      <esp:link page="unifeat">Unicode extension and adaptation
      mechanisms</esp:link> and <esp:link page="opentype">OpenType
      font features</esp:link> to ensure that the cuneiform is displayed as
      required and intended without undermining data consistency.</p>

      <esp:h>Fonts</esp:h>

      <p>Some fonts are extremely inclusive and attempt to capture the
      entire history of cuneiform signs in a single font, some reflect
      only a single period or sub-corpus, and some fall somewhere in
      between.  Oracc currently provides the following fonts:</p>

      <dl>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-noto">Oracc Noto</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>An extremely inclusive font covering all of Unicode
	cuneiform and more.</dd>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-pc">PCSL</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>The Proto-Cuneiform font to accompany <esp:link
	url="http://oracc.org">the PCSL project</esp:link></dd>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-lak">Oracc LAK</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>Oracc LAK, for an overview of Early Dynastic/Third Millennium sign forms.</dd>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-rsp">Oracc RSP</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>Oracc RSP, for an overview of Early Dynastic IIIb sign forms.</dd>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-gudea">Oracc Gudea</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>Oracc Gudea, for Gudea sign forms.</dd>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-oobf">Oracc OBF</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>Oracc OB-Freie, for Old Babylonian sign forms.</dd>
	<dt><esp:link page="ofs-nao">Oracc NA Outline</esp:link></dt>
	<dd>Oracc NA Outline, for Neo-Assyrian sign forms.</dd>
      </dl>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>

