<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Oracc Cuneiform Fonts</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Oracc Cuneiform Fonts</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <esp:h>Introduction</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc provides a number of cuneiform fonts which aim to
      provide some degree of consistency and standardization in their
      approach to character definition and use of font technology.
      This is possible even when the Oracc fonts are versions of fonts
      which were not originally intended for use on Oracc but which
      have been generously licensed under terms which permit modifying
      them in the ways required for alignment with Oracc font
      approaches.</p>

      <p>Oracc fonts are all based on Unicode, and make use of both
      Unicode extension and adaptation mechanisms and OpenType font
      features to ensure that the cuneiform is displayed as required
      and intended without undermining data consistency.</p>

      <esp:h>Unicode Features</esp:h>

      <esp:sh>The Unicode Private Use Area (PUA)</esp:sh>

      <p>Oracc uses the Unicode Plane 15 PUA from F0000-FFFFD as a
      space to create signs pending possible encoding, and to maintain
      variant forms of signs that do not merit separate encoding
      ("impossible" numbers like 4(eše@c) would fall into this
      category, for example). All management of the Oracc PUA is
      consolidated in the OSL project and is further described on the
      <esp:link page="oracc-pua">Oracc PUA page</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:sh>Unicode Ideographic Variation Sequences (IVS)</esp:sh>

      <p>An IVS consists of a two parts: a sign and a variant
      selector.  Oracc uses IVS to support encoding structurally
      distinct graphic variants of the same sign in such a way that
      both the identity of the sign and the identity of the structural
      variant are preserved.</p>

      <p>For example, the DE₂ sign U+12423 can be written in several
      different ways: |UMUM×KASKAL| (the reference glyph in the
      Unicode Standard); UMUM@s; and |UMUM×PA|.  If a font supports
      IVS sequences such as u12423_uE0100=|UMUM×KASKAL|;
      u12423_uE0101=UMUM@s; u12433_uE0102 then it is possible to
      encode the data so that the Unicode sign U+12423=DE₂ is still
      the primary data element, but the way that it is written is also
      preserved.  See the <esp:link page="oracc-ivs">Oracc IVS
      page</esp:link> for further details.</p>

      <p>For conciseness and legibility Oracc documentation notates
      IVS in font character naming form, e.g., u12423_uE0102.  In some
      contexts an abbreviated notation is used, i.e.,
      [CHARACTER-NAME].eNN, were NN are the last two digits of an IVS
      selector.</p>
      
      <p>Oracc uses OpenType SSET and SALT for other kinds of graphic
      variation as described below.</p>

      <esp:h>OpenType Features</esp:h>

      <esp:p>OpenType is a widely-used font type created by Microsoft
      and Adobe which provides many features for advanced typography.
      Oracc uses only three OpenType features at present: SSET, SALT,
      and LIGA.</esp:p>
      
      <esp:sh>Sylistic Sets (SSET)</esp:sh>
      
      <p>An OpenType font can have up to twenty Stylistic Sets,
      indicated as ss01, ss02 .. ss20.  Oracc uses SSET for
      collections of variations which correspond to usages typical of
      a period, styles related to a medium, or general handwriting
      styles.  For example, Oracc uses ss01 for early writing styles
      which exhibit certain mergers that take place immediately after
      the Fara period; ss02 for middle period mergers; ss03 for later
      mergers and splits.  Sset ss04 is reserved for monumental
      script--so a Neo-Babylonian font could have sign forms typical
      of writing on stone in ss04, for example. Sset ss05 is reserved
      for cursive style writing.</p>

      <esp:sh>Character Variants (CVNN)</esp:sh>

      <p>An OpenType font may have up to ninety-nine character
      variants.  The following explananation of CVNN is to be found in
      the <esp:link
      url="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/typography/opentype/spec/features_ae#tag-cv01--cv99">Learn/Microsoft
      Typography description of Tag: 'cv01' – 'cv99'</esp:link>:</p>

      <blockquote>
	The function of these features is similar to the function of
	the Stylistic Alternates feature ('salt') and the Stylistic
	Set features (see 'ss01' – 'ss20'). Whereas the Stylistic Set
	features assume recurring stylistic variations that apply to a
	broad set of Unicode characters, however, these features are
	intended for scenarios in which particular characters have
	variations not applicable to a broad set of characters. The
	Stylistic Alternates feature provides access to glyph variants
	but does not allow an application to control these on a
	character-by-character basis; the Character Variant features
	provide the greater granularity of control.
      </blockquote>

      <p>The kinds of character variation that Oracc might use with
      CV--stacking pattern variations, character composition
      variations--can also be supported with IVS (see above).  Because
      of the 99 CV limit imposed by OpenType fonts it is preferable to
      support these kinds of variation through the IVS mechanism.</p>
      
      <esp:sh>Stylistic Alternates (SALT)</esp:sh>

      <p>Oracc uses SALT to support creating fonts which contain
      examples of minor variations in form that may be specific to an
      instance, a scribe, or a school--many sign lists that are
      restricted to a particular period or corpus demonstrate several
      variant forms of signs, and a font that emulates such a list can
      use SALT to encode these variants.</p>

      <p>SALT variations are font-specific and do not need to be
      aligned or harmonized across fonts.</p>

      <esp:sh>Ligatures (LIGA)</esp:sh>

      <p>There are several kinds of OpenType ligatures, but Oracc
      consistently uses the LIGA feature ("Standard Ligatures") which
      are automatically selected in a font when the components occur
      in sequence.</p>

      <p>Some ligatures are defined to work only when there is a
      U+200D, Zero-Width Joiner (ZWJ) character between the
      components.  For example, this allows the sequence diŋir-en to
      be treated as two characters or a single ligatured character as
      required (scribes sometimes mix their use on a single
      tablet).</p>

      <esp:h>Fonts</esp:h>

      <p>Some fonts are extremely inclusive and attempt to capture the
      entire history of cuneiform signs in a single font, some reflect
      only a single period or sub-corpus, and some fall somewhere in
      between.  <esp:link page="fonts">See the fonts page for
      information on each of the Oracc fonts.</esp:link>.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>

