<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Oracc Ideographic Variation</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Oracc Ideographic Variation</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>This page describes an experimental implementation of Unicode
      Ideographic Variation Sequences as defined in <esp:link
      url="https://unicode.org/reports/tr37">Unicode Technical Report
      37 (referred to as TR37 in the following).</esp:link> in OSL and
      Oracc fonts. The original idea of using these with Unicode
      cuneiform is owed to Robin LeRoy.</p>

      <esp:h>Overview</esp:h>

      <p>Unicode IVSs provide a means for selecting glyph variants in
      a standardized way.  They work as a character pair in which the
      second character is a selector for a glyph variant of the first.
      The selectors are in the range U+E0100-U+E01EF.</p>

      <p>The Unicode Ideographic Variation Database, IVD, as defined
      in TR37 is very simple: a collection must be registered with
      basic metadata. A complementary file defines sequences in the
      collection consisting of pairs of base characters and variation
      selectors along with a collection name and a name for the
      sequence.</p>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OSL Collection</esp:h>

      <p>The name of the Oracc OSL collection is
      <code>Oracc_OSL</code>. This implementation is presently
      unregistered, but the collection data would be of the form:</p>

      <pre>
	Oracc_OSL;[A-Z]+[0-9]*(?:[@%&amp;*.][A-Z]+[0-9]*)*_[A-Z]+[0-9]*(?:[@%&amp;*.][A-Z]+[0-9]*)*;http://oracc.org/osl/ivs/
      </pre>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OSL Identifier Structure</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc_OSL identifiers consist of a BASESIGN, underscore
      character, '_', and VARDATA.  Both BASESIGN, the sign subject to
      variation, and VARDATA, the variation, consist of uppercase
      letters A-Z followed by optional digits 0-9, followed by
      optional compound sign parts.  A compound sign part consists of
      a delimiter from the set <code>@%&amp;*.</code> plus a sign
      name, consisting of uppercase letters A-Z followed by optional
      digits 0-9.</p>

      <p>The BASESIGN is always derived from an OSL sign name
      translating subscript digits to regular digits and substituting
      SH for Š, e.g., <code>MU</code>, <code>NI2</code>, or
      <code>SHU</code>.  For compound signs the sign name is
      simplified by omitting vertical bars and parentheses and mapping
      any TIMES sign to '*', e.g., <code>|GA₂×AN|</code> would be
      specified as <code>GA2*AN</code>.</p>

      <p>The VARDATA is either an OSL sign name or a descriptive
      label for the variant selected via the sequence as described
      further in the next section.</p>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OSL Reference Glyphs</esp:h>

      <p>A table of Oracc_OSL reference glyphs will be maintained at
      XXX/osl/ivsglyphs.html.</p>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OSL use of Variation Selectors</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc_OSL defines IVSs for two reasons to support research
      annotation of cuneiform texts where it is important to encode
      both the base sign and its paleographic variant forms.</p>
      
      <p>An example would be that a variation of the MU sign, mostly
      associated with ED Adab, is to form the SHE-style component of
      the sign with a KASKAL-style component instead:</p>

      <pre>
	# MU sign with KASKAL-style replacement for normal SHE-style component
	1222C E0100;Oracc_OSL;MU_KASKAL
      </pre>

      <p>In the case of variant forms, The VARDATA component of the
      label <code>MU_KASKAL</code> may qualify the variation rather
      than defining the target form as a merged sign.</p>

      <esp:h>Oracc_OSL Ideographic Variation Database</esp:h>

      <p>The Oracc_OSL Ideographic Variation Database, OIVD, is kept
      in 00etc/Oracc_OSL.txt in the Oracc OSL repo, and is available
      online at XXX.</p>

      <p>The OIVD contains all possible applications of IVS in
      Oracc_OSL; not all script phases will exhibit all IVS traits,
      however.</p>

      <esp:h>Implementation Notes</esp:h>

      <esp:sh>Fonts</esp:sh>

      <p>In Oracc cuneiform fonts IVS sequences are treated <esp:link
      url="/osl/OraccCuneiformFonts#h_ligaturesliga">as OpenType LIGA
      entries</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:sh>Annotation</esp:sh>

      <p>In Oracc's transliteration system IVS sequences will be
      selectable using <esp:link
      url="/osl/OraccCuneiformFonts/OSLGraphetics">OSL Graphetics
      tags.</esp:link>.</p>
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
