<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Oracc Cuneiform Fonts</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Oracc Cuneiform Fonts</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
      <esp:h>Introduction</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc provides a number of cuneiform fonts which aim to
      provide some degree of consistency and standardization in their
      approach to character definition and use of font technology.
      This is possible even when the Oracc fonts are versions of fonts
      which were not originally intended for use on Oracc but which
      have been generously licensed under terms which permit modifying
      them in the ways required for alignment with Oracc font
      approaches.</p>

      <p>Oracc fonts are all based on Unicode, and make use of both
      Unicode extension and adaptation mechanisms and OpenType font
      features to ensure that the cuneiform is displayed as required
      and intended without undermining data consistency.</p>

      <esp:h>Unicode Features</esp:h>

      <esp:sh>The Unicode Private Use Area (PUA)</esp:sh>

      <p>Oracc uses the Unicode Plane 15 PUA from F0000-FFFFD as a
      space to create signs pending possible encoding, and to maintain
      variant forms of signs that do not merit separate encoding. All
      management of the Oracc PUA is consolidated in the OSL project
      and is further described on the <esp:link page="oracc-pua">Oracc
      PUA page</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:sh>Unicode Ideographic Variation Sequences (IVS)</esp:sh>

      <p>An IVS consists of a two parts: a sign and a variant
      indicator.  Oracc uses IVS to support encoding structurally
      distinct graphic variants of the same sign in such a way that
      both the identity of the sign and the identity of the structural
      variant are preserved.  For example, the DE₂ sign U+12423 can be
      written in several different ways: |UMUM×KASKAL| (the reference
      glyph in the Unicode Standard); UMUM@s; and |UMUM×PA|.  See the
      <esp:link page="oracc-ivs">Oracc IVS page</esp:link> for further
      details.</p>

      <p>Oracc uses OpenType SALT and Character Variation features for
      their other kinds of graphic variation as described below.</p>

      <esp:h>OpenType Features</esp:h>

      <esp:sh>Sylistic Sets (SSET)</esp:sh>
      
      <p>An OpenType font can have up to twenty Stylistic Sets,
      indicated as ss01, ss02 .. ss20.  Oracc uses SSET for
      collections of variations which correspond to usages typical of
      a period, styles related to a medium, or general handwriting
      styles.  For example, Oracc uses ss01 for early writing styles
      which exhibit certain mergers that take place immediately after
      the Fara period; ss02 for middle period mergers; ss03 for later
      mergers and splits.  Sset ss04 is reserved for monumental
      script--so an Neo-Babylonian font could have sign forms typical
      of writing on stone in ss04, for example. Sset ss05 is reserved
      for cursive style writing.</p>

      <esp:sh>Character Variants (CVNN)</esp:sh>

      <p>An OpenType font can have up to one hundred character
      variants, indicated as cv01, cv02 .. cv99.  Oracc uses CVNN for
      character variations which may be common to multiple fonts but
      which are not structurally distinct.  One class of CVNN is
      variant stacking patterns for numbers--consistent CVNN numbering
      for patterns allows multiple fonts to render the same stacking
      pattern by using the same CVNN suffix.</p>

      <esp:sh>Stylistic Alternates (SALT)</esp:sh>

      <p>Oracc uses SALT to support creating fonts which contain
      examples of minor variations in form that may be specific to an
      instance, a scribe, or a school--many sign lists that are
      restricted to a particular period or corpus demonstrate several
      variant forms of signs, and a font that emulates such a list can
      use SALT to encode these variants.</p>

      <esp:sh>Ligatures (LIGA)</esp:sh>

      <p>There are several kinds of OpenType ligatures, but Oracc
      consistently uses the LIGA feature ("Standard Ligatures") which
      are automatically selected in a font when the components occur
      in sequence.</p>

      <p>Some ligatures are defined to work only when there is a
      U+200D, Zero-Width Joiner (ZWJ) character between the
      components.  For example, this allows the sequence diŋir-en to
      be treated as two characters or a single ligatured character as
      required (scribes sometimes mix their use on a single
      tablet).</p>

      <esp:h>Fonts</esp:h>

      <p>Some fonts are extremely inclusive and attempt to capture the
      entire history of cuneiform signs in a single font, some reflect
      only a single period or sub-corpus, and some fall somewhere in
      between.  <esp:link page="fonts">See the fonts page for
      information on each of the Oracc fonts.</esp:link>.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>

