<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Oracc PUA</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Oracc PUA</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>
<p>Oracc uses the Plane 15 PUA from F0000-FFFFD as a space to create
signs pending possible encoding, and to maintain variant forms of
signs that do not merit separate encoding. All management of the Oracc
PUA is consolidated in the OSL project.</p>

<p>The region from F0000-F0FFF is used for core Oracc additions; the
region from F1000 are used for font-specific additions.</p>

<esp:h>Retention Policy</esp:h>

<p>Characters are added to the Oracc PUA from F0000-F0FFF are
considered permanent and are never removed.  If a PUA character is
subsequently encoded the OSL is updated to reflect the encoded
character but the version in the PUA is left as it is.</p>

<p>Characters from F1000 upwards should be considered impermanent and
are used for font development where a period of refinement may make it
convenient to maintain a number of characters pending resolution of
their fate.</p>

<esp:h>Definitional Data Table</esp:h>

<p>A running account of the PUA usage is kept in <esp:link
url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/oracc/osl/refs/heads/master/00etc/oracc-pua.tab">oracc-pua.tab</esp:link>.</p>

<p>The data format for this table is:</p>

<pre>
OID        SIGN-NAME      PUA-CODE      SCRIPT     ORACC-PUA-BLOCK	NOTES
</pre>

<dd>
  <dt>OID</dt>
  <dd>An OID must be assigned in Oracc's OID table for any character
  that is being added to the Oracc PUA.</dd>

  <dt>SIGN-NAME</dt>
  <dd>The primary OSL name for the sign</dd>
  
  <dt>PUA-CODE</dt>
  <dd>The uppercase hex codepoint in Plane 15.</dd>

  <dt>SCRIPT</dt>
  <dd>One of the script codes Xsux, Pcun, Pelm.</dd>

  <dt>ORACC-PUA-BLOCK</dt>
  <dd>An indicator of groups of characters added to the Oracc PUA; by
  convention these are numbered 9.x.</dd>

  <dt>NOTES</dt>
  <dd>Provides various information on the source of characters and
  possible implementations/future resolutions of their status.  The
  notation NAME.eNN in this column means that the sign can be treated
  as IVS E0100+NN of the character NAME.</dd>
</dd>

<esp:sh>More on the Notes Column</esp:sh>

<p>In Oracc PUA 9.5 the following abbreviations are used (some of
these should be generalized to other parts of the Oracc PUA):</p>

<dl>
  <dt>ACN</dt><dd>"Archaic Cuneiform Numerals [Encode]"--the character
  could be encoded in a future ACN additions proposal.</dd>

  <dt>ADD</dt><dd>"Additional"--a neutral designation
  indicating only that the character is not in ACN. Characters
  above U+F0000 are not in AP23 either.</dd>

  <dt>DNE</dt><dd>"Do Not Encode"--the character is not encodable.</dd>
  
  <dt>OOR</dt><dd>"Out Of Range"--an assertion that the
  character is anomalous and should not be encoded.</dd>

  <dt>Pelm</dt><dd>Proto-Elamite--the character should be
  encoded in the Proto-Elamite proposal.</dd>
  
  <dt>PCE</dt><dd>"Proto-Cuneiform Encode"--the character
  should be encoded in the PC proposal.</dd>
</dl>

<esp:h>Oracc PUA Blocks</esp:h>

<esp:sh>Block 9.1</esp:sh>

<p>This block was created in September/October 2024 for number signs and
variants that were not encoded at that point.</p>

<p>The OSL/signlist <esp:link url="/osl/signlist/OraccPUA9.1/">has a PUA 9.1 page</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>Block 9.2</esp:sh>

<p>This block was created in October 2024 for non-numerical signs and
variants that were not encoded at that point.</p>

<p>The OSL/signlist <esp:link url="/osl/signlist/OraccPUA9.2/">has a PUA 9.2 page</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>Block 9.3</esp:sh>

<p>Created November 2024 for Variant Stacking Patterns in Pcun.</p>

<p>The OSL/signlist <esp:link url="/osl/signlist/OraccPUA9.3/">has a PUA 9.3 page</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>Block 9.4</esp:sh>

<p>Created November 2024 for unencodable Pcun numbers.</p>

<p>The OSL/signlist <esp:link url="/osl/signlist/OraccPUA9.4/">has a PUA 9.4 page</esp:link>.</p>

<esp:sh>Block 9.5</esp:sh>

<p>Created November 2024 for possibly encodable Pcun numbers.</p>

<p>The OSL/signlist <esp:link url="/osl/signlist/OraccPUA9.5/">has a PUA 9.5 page</esp:link>.</p>

    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
