<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>The OSL Font</esp:name>
  <esp:title>The OSL Font</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <!--note: this is a preliminary design document; implementation
           experience may result in revisions-->
      
      <p>OSL provides an OpenType font based on Cuneiform Noto which
      covers all of the OSL sign repertoire, some of which are located
      in the Unicode Private Use Area in plane 15 (U+F0000–U+FFFFD)
      and supports sign-mergers and variants by using the OpenType
      Stylistic Variation and SALT features, as well as ligatures
      implemented using Unicode Ideographic Variation Selectors in the
      range U+E0100 to U+E01EF.</p>

      <p>The current FontLab source for the OSL font is available as
      <esp:link
      url="https://github.com/oracc/oracc2/raw/refs/heads/main/lib/fonts/Noto-SansCuneiform-OSL.vfc">Noto-SansCuneiform-OSL.vfc</esp:link>. The
      OpenType version is delivered as a web font which means it is
      not necessary for individual users to download it; it is
      available as <esp:link
      url="https://github.com/oracc/oracc2/raw/refs/heads/main/lib/fonts/Noto-SansCuneiform-OSL.ttf">Noto-SansCuneiform-OSL.ttf</esp:link>
      for use with other applications.</p>

      <esp:sh>OSL Script Concepts</esp:sh>

      <p>OSL script variation is accessible in various ways. Common
      sets of variants are grouped into named script-styles which
      correspond to OpenType Stylistic Sets. These script-styles
      implement general variations such as the common merger of IM
      with NI₂ but are not intended to capture individual
      manuscript-level variation. A script-style may have individual
      character variants in addition to the Stylistic Set.</p>
      
      <p>The following script-styles are presently defined:</p>

      <table class="pretty">
	<tr><td>Script-style</td><td>OT Stylistic Set</td></tr>
	<tr><td>Default</td><td>(none)</td><td>Selects standard font glyphs.</td></tr>
	<tr><td>Early</td><td>ss01</td><td>Selects Early Dynastic glyph forms.</td></tr>
	<tr><td>Middle</td><td>ss02</td><td>Selects Ur III/OB glyph forms.</td></tr>
	<tr><td>Late</td><td>ss03</td><td>Selects later mergers.</td></tr>
	<tr><td>Gudea</td><td>ss02</td><td>Selects Ur III/OB glyphs
	along with de₂=UMUM@s.</td></tr>
      </table>

      <p>OSL script-styles can be selected in a project configuration
      file or in an ATF protocol.</p>

      <p>Configuration file:</p>

      <pre>&lt;option name="osl-script-style" value="gudea"/></pre>

      <p>ATF protocol:</p>

      <pre>#atf: script gudea</pre>

      <p>Individual character variants may be automatically selected
      via transliteration based on the value or sign/form name or they
      may be selectable using a graphetic suffix, e.g., de₂\s might
      select the UMUM@s version of DE₂ which would be an alternative
      to transliterating as de₂(UMUM@s).</p>
      
      <esp:sh>OSL Script-style Definitions</esp:sh>

      <p>Script-styles are defined in osl.asl.  A script-style label
      is defined using @scriptdef:</p>

      <pre>@scriptdef gudea ss03</pre>

      <p>Script-style information is added to signs and forms with
      @script, which must be repeated for each script-style that is
      required for a given sign.</p>

      <p>The first argument to @script must be a script-style label as
      defined with @scriptdef, followed by a colon. The following
      arguments are a semi-colon-separated list of directives ending
      with a period.</p>

      <p>The following directives are supported:</p>

      <dl>
	<dt>ivs U+[IVSCODE]</dt><dd>The ivs directive specifies an IVS
	codepoint which can be paired with the current sign's @ucun to
	create a ligature that will select the appropriate variant for
	the sign in the given script-style.</dd>
	
	<dt>merge > [SIGN]</dt><dd>The merge directive indicates that
	the current sign merges with the SIGN given after the '>';
	e.g., <code>@script gudea: merge >NI₂</code>.  This is not
	used by the font technology, but is used when building
	period-specific sub-signlists.
      </dd>

	<dt>salt [NUMBER]</dt><dd>The salt directive indicates that
	the current sign should be replaced by the script-alternative
	sign specified by [NUMBER].  Note that [NUMBER] must be
	specified even if it is '1'.</dd>
      </dl>

      <esp:sh>ATF and Script-styles</esp:sh>

      <p>The OSL processor, sx, generates script-style data that can
      be used by the ATF processor.  If a script-style is
      given in the project configuration file it is output in the
      osl-script attribute of all texts in the project.  If a
      script-style is given in an ATF protocol, it is output in the
      osl-script attribute of the current text; both methods can be
      used, with the protocol overriding the configuration file.</p>

      <p>If salt or ivs directives are given for a sign, corresponding
      attributes are added on grapheme nodes besides the utf8
      attribute.  For salt the attribute value is the number; for ivs
      the attribute value is the Unicode cuneiform sequence consisting
      of the base sign and the IVS, given in UTF-8 encoding.</p>
      
    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>
