<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<esp:page xmlns:esp="http://oracc.org/ns/esp/1.0"
	  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xh="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	  xmlns:xpd="http://oracc.org/ns/xpd/1.0">
  <esp:name>Unicode Features</esp:name>
  <esp:title>Unicode Features</esp:title>
  <html>
    <head/>
    <body>

      <p>Oracc, OSL, and other Oracc sign lists aim to be completely
      conformant to the Unicode standard while supporting paleographic
      fidelity down to the level of individual handwriting as well as
      the best degree of automated cuneiform typography that is
      reasonably possible.</p>
      
      <esp:h>The Unicode Private Use Area (PUA)</esp:h>

      <p>Oracc uses the Unicode Plane 15 PUA from F0000-FFFFD as a
      space to create signs pending possible encoding, and to maintain
      variant forms of signs that do not merit separate encoding
      ("impossible" numbers like 4(eše@c) would fall into this
      category, for example). All management of the Oracc PUA is
      consolidated in the OSL project and is further described on the
      <esp:link page="oracc-pua">Oracc PUA page</esp:link>.</p>

      <esp:h>Unicode Ideographic Variation Sequences (IVS)</esp:h>

      <p>An IVS consists of a two parts: a sign and a variant
      selector.  Oracc uses IVS to support encoding structurally
      distinct graphic variants of the same sign in such a way that
      both the identity of the sign and the identity of the structural
      variant are preserved.  IVS provides a means of preserving the
      integrity of paleographic differences without requiring
      additional character encodings.</p>

      <p>For example, the DE₂ sign U+12423 can be written in several
      different ways: |UMUM×KASKAL| (the reference glyph in the
      Unicode Standard); UMUM@s; and |UMUM×PA|.  If a font supports
      IVS sequences such as u12423_uE0100=|UMUM×KASKAL|;
      u12423_uE0101=UMUM@s; u12433_uE0102 then it is possible to
      encode the data so that the Unicode sign U+12423=DE₂ is still
      the primary data element, but the way that it is written is also
      preserved.  See the <esp:link page="oracc-ivs">Oracc IVS
      page</esp:link> for further details.</p>

      <p>For conciseness and legibility Oracc documentation notates
      IVS in font character naming form, e.g., u12423_uE0102.  In some
      contexts an abbreviated notation is used, i.e.,
      [CHARACTER-NAME].eNN, were NN are the last two digits of an IVS
      selector.</p>

      <p>The Oracc implementation of this feature is immature and
      presently non-compliant with the Unicode standard.</p>

      <esp:h>Other Mechanisms</esp:h>
      
      <p>Oracc uses OpenType SSET and SALT for other kinds of graphic
      variation as described on <esp:link page="opentype-features">the
      OpenType Features page</esp:link>.</p>

    </body>
  </html>
</esp:page>

